<!--
~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com) ~ ~ Licensed under
the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); ~ you may not use
this file except in compliance with the License. ~ You may obtain a
copy of the License at ~ ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
~ ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
BASIS, ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express
or implied. ~ See the License for the specific language governing
permissions and ~ limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<body>

		<h1>Carbon Tools</h1>
		<h2>Content</h2>
		<div class="toc">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="#JavaLibArtifact">Java Library Project</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#CarbonUIArtifact">Carbon UI Bundle Project</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</div>
		<h2 id="JavaLibArtifact">Java Library Project</h2>		
        <p>
        With <strong>Java Library Project</strong>, you can refer a <strong>jar</strong> file or 
        a <strong>project in your workspace</strong> and make it a bundle which will be available 
        in to bundle classpath during the runtime. 
        </p>
        <p>
        To create a <strong>Java Library Project</strong>, open <strong>WSO2 Developer Studio Dashboard</strong> 
        and select <strong>Java Library Project</strong> from <strong>Carbon</strong> category. 
        </p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib1.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		Give a name to the project and click <strong>Next</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib2.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		There are two ways to create a Java Library Artifact.    
		</p>
		<ol>
			<li>From File System</li>
			<li>From Workspace</li>
		</ol>
		
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib3.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>

		<p>With the <strong>File System</strong> option, you can point to a jar file of the file system which you may use in 
		the when creating your SOA application.
		</p>
			
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib4.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
			
		<p>With the second option, it will list all the available projects in the workspace and you can select the project 
		you want to create a Java Library dependency.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib5.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		You can add multiple jars and projects for a single <strong>Java Library Project</strong>. 
		Once you add needed jars and projects, click <strong>Finish</strong>.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib6.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		Now you will see <strong>Library Project</strong> has been created in the workspace. You 
		can create a bundle out of that project by exporting it in to a deployable archive. To do that
		right click on the project and select <strong>Export Project as Deployable Archive</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/lib7.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		You can do the same thing by grouping the created <strong>Library Project</strong> in to 
		a <strong>Carbon Application Project</strong> and make a <strong>Carbon Application 
		Archive</strong> out of it. 
		</p>
		
		<h2 id="CarbonUIArtifact">Carbon UI Bundle Project</h2>
        <p>
        To create a <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong>, open <strong>WSO2 Developer Studio Dashboard</strong> 
        and select <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong> from <strong>Carbon</strong> category. 
        </p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui1.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		You can create a <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong> in two different ways. 
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Create New Carbon UI Bundle</li>
			<li>Import Carbon UI Bundle From Workspace</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui2.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		With <strong>New Carbon UI Bundle</strong> option, you will create a new bundle project 
		from the scratch. In the wizard page, you will see an entry called 
		<strong>Deploy Path</strong> with entries to enter other necessary information. 
		<strong>Deploy Path</strong> is the path where you specify all your resources like 
		<strong>jsp files, html files</strong> etc. Give the necessary information and click 
		<strong>Finish</strong>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui3.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		Now you will see new <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong> has been created in the 
		workspace.  
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui4.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		You will see a folder structure has been created according to the 
		<strong>Deploy Path</strong> you have specified.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui5.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		With <strong>Import Carbon UI Bundle From Workspace</strong> option, you can refer already defined  
		<strong>Carbon UI Bundle Components</strong> in the workspace. With <strong>WSO2 Developer Studio</strong> 
		you can create <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Component</strong> as well. This will be a stand-alone 
		<strong>Eclipse Plugin Project</strong> with customizations relevant to make it a <strong>Carbon 
		UI Bundle</strong>. This option is available under <strong>File -> New -> Other -> Carbon -> 
		Carbon UI Component</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbon3.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
			
		<p>This also includes the same data as you entered when creating a <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong>. 
		Give necessary information and click <strong>Finish</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbon4.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbon5.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>			
		<p>Now you will see a new project has been created in the workspace. These projects will 
		be available when you select the <strong>Import Carbon UI Bundle From Workspace</strong> 
		option when creating a <strong>Carbon UI Bundle Project</strong>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/carbonui6.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		You can add your jsps/js/html files under the folder structure created according to the 
		<strong>Deploy Path</strong> you have specified. 
		</p>	
		<p>
		As you did for all the other projects, you can export the created <strong>Carbon UI Bundle 
		Project</strong> in to a deployable artifact by right click on the project and select
		 <strong>Export Project as Deployable Archive</strong>. With this it will create you a 
		 bundle which you can deploy in to any <strong>Carbon Server</strong>. At the same time, 
		 you can group it with a <strong>Carbon Application Project</strong> and create the 
		 <strong>Carbon Application Archive</strong> as well. 
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
