<!--
~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com) ~ ~ Licensed under
the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); ~ you may not use
this file except in compliance with the License. ~ You may obtain a
copy of the License at ~ ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
~ ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
BASIS, ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express
or implied. ~ See the License for the specific language governing
permissions and ~ limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<body>

		<h1>Data Service Tools</h1>
		<h2>Content</h2>
		<div class="toc">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="#DSArtifact">Data Service Project</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="server_extensions_category.html#DSValidator">Data Service Validator</a>
				</li>				
			</ul>
		</div>
		<h2 id="DSArtifact">Data Service Project</h2>
        <p>
       	To create a <strong>Data Service Project</strong>, open <strong>WSO2 Developer Studio Dashboard</strong> 
        and select <strong>Data Service Project</strong> from <strong>Data Services Server</strong> category. 
        </p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp1.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		There are two ways to create a data service.    
		</p>
		<ol>
			<li>New Data Service</li>
			<li>Import Data Service</li>
		</ol>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp2.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>

		<p>With the <strong>New Data Service</strong> option, you will get an empty data service according to 
		the information that you have provided. At the same time, you can upload a 
		<strong>Data Service Descriptor</strong> file with the extension of <strong>.dbs</strong> from the 
		file system.
		</p>
		<p>
		If you select <strong>New Data Service</strong> option, and click <strong>Next</strong>, wizard page 
		will ask you general information like <strong>Project Name</strong>, <strong>Data Service Name</strong> 
		etc. Give necessary information and click <strong>Next</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp3.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		In the next page, you need to specify information regarding the <strong>Data Source</strong> that 
		you are going to use in your data service. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp4.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		There are several defined data sources. Information below will be filled according to the 
		<strong>Database Engine</strong> you have selected. Suppose I select <strong>MySQL</strong> 
		as my <strong>Database Engine</strong>. As you can see, <strong>Driver Class</strong> and 
		the format of <strong>JDBC URL</strong> will be filled for you. You have to specify 
		<strong>User Name</strong> field and <strong>Password</strong> field. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp5.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		After giving necessary information, click <strong>Finish</strong>. Now you will see that the 
		created <strong>Data Service</strong> has opened with <strong>Graphical Data Services Editor</strong>.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp6.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
		With this <strong>Graphical Editor</strong>, you can add different <strong>Data Sources, Queries,
		Operations</strong> etc in a very convenient manner. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp7.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<!--  <p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp8.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>-->
		
		<p>
		If you are quite familiar with Data Services Descriptor language, you can navigate to source view and 
		add components. Source view is fully functioned with <strong>content assist</strong> capability which 
		will ease the pain of editing to great level.  
		</p>
		<p>With the <strong>Import Data Service</strong> option, you can browse for data service 
		descriptor (dbs) file in your file system.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp9.png"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>	
		<p>
		Now you will see a new <strong>Data Service Project</strong> has been created in the workspace and the 
		<strong>data service descriptor (dbs) file</strong> open with graphical editor.
		</p>
			<p>
				<br></br>
				<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/dsp10.png"></img>
				<br></br>
			</p>	
			
		<p>
		As you did for all the other projects, you can export the created <strong>Data Service 
		Project</strong> in to a deployable artifact by right click on the project and select
		 <strong>Export Project as Deployable Archive</strong>. With this it will create you a 
		 <strong>dbs</strong> file, which you can deploy in to any 
		 <strong>WSO2 Data Services Server</strong>. At the same time, 
		 you can group it with a <strong>Carbon Application Project</strong> and create the 
		 <strong>Carbon Application Archive [CAR]</strong> and deploy in to the <strong>Carbon 
		 Server</strong>. 
		</p>		
									
	</body>
</html>
