<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com) ~ ~ Licensed under 
	the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); ~ you may not use this file 
	except in compliance with the License. ~ You may obtain a copy of the License 
	at ~ ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 ~ ~ Unless required by 
	applicable law or agreed to in writing, software ~ distributed under the 
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS 
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. ~ See the License for the specific 
	language governing permissions and ~ limitations under the License. -->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<body>

		<h1>How To Refer a Dynamic Sequence in ESB Graphical Editor</h1>
		<p>
			Dynamic Sequence in WSO2 ESB Configuration language means a Sequence which
			is stored in WSO2 ESB Registry. Thus referring to a Dynamic Sequence
			in your mediation flow means WSO2 ESB looks up the Registry of WSO2
			ESB during the runtime and locate the appropriate Registry Resource
			in the Registry using the user defined Registry Key in the
			Configuration.
</p>
		<p>
			In this section of the document we explain how you can refer to a
			Dynamic Sequence from a mediation flow.
</p>

		<div class="toc">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="#method1">Refer to a Dynamic Sequence stored in a Registry Resource
						Project</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#method2">Refer to a Dynamic Sequence Stored in Registry during the
						Development Time</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</div>
		<h2 id="method1">Refer to a Dynamic Sequence stored in a Registry Resource
			Project</h2>
		<p>WSO2 Developer Studio supports a project type called “Registry
			Resources Project” which can be used to store Resources and
			Collections you want to deploy to Registry of a Carbon Server using
			Carbon Application Project (C-App). Therefore it is possible for you
			to maintain your Dynamic Sequence in a Registry Resource Project and
			refer to that Sequence from the mediation flow. In the runtime when
			you deploy the CAR file with both Registry Resource and Mediation
			flow, WSO2 ESB will resolve the Reference key and use the Registry
			Resource from the Registry.</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence1.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Once you complete the Sequence design, you can save it and open the
			mediation flow you need to refer to it.
</p>
		<p>
			Then you need to click on the Sequence mediator in the Tool Palette and
			click on the Canvas area of the editor.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence2.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Then select the Sequence mediator you placed on the Canvas area and
			click on the small button in the Static Reference Key property in
			Eclipse properties view as shown in the image below.</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence3.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Then editor will populate the Resource Key Editor dialog where you
			can use to look in to resources in your Developer Studio workspace.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence4.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Click on the “workspace” link button as indicated and Editor will
			populate the Workspace Element Provider dialog where all the
			resources in your Developer Studio workspace are listed and sorted
			according to their Resource Type and then according to their Project
			location as shown below.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence5.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Once you select a Resource from this dialog, Mediation flow will be
			updated accordingly with the corresponding Registry Reference Key as
			shown in the image.
			</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence6.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<h2 id="method2">Refer to a Dynamic Sequence Stored in Registry during the
			Development Time</h2>
		<p>
			Since Dynamic Sequences are stored in the Registry, Developer Studio ESB
			Editor supports referring to Resources stored in remote and local
			Registry instances as well.
</p>
		<p>
			First you need add the Sequence mediator to your mediation flow. Therefore
			click on the Sequence mediator on the Tool Palette and then click on
			the Canvas area.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence2.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Then click on the button at the end of the Static Reference Key
			property in Eclipse properties view as shown below.</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence3.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>When you click on that, Editor will open the Resource Key Editor
			dialog as shown below.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence4_1.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Then click on the Registry link on this dialog and it will populate the
			Registry Browser dialog for you.
</p>
		<p>
			Using this Registry Browser dialog you can connect to running remote and
			local Registry instances. 
</p>
		<p>
			To connect with such a Registry instance, first you need to click on
			the “Add Registry” button on the Registry Browser Dialog. This will
			populate the simple dialog requesting you to provide the URL and the
			Path you want to connect with in the Registry instance.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence7.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Once you provide the URL and Path to the Registry instance, it will add a
			registry element to the Registry Browser. Once you click on that,
			Registry Browser will populate a dialog requesting you to enter
			Credentials to access this Registry instance.
</p>
		<p>
			When you provide the correct credentials, you will be able to browse the
			Registry instance in the same manner you browse it using Management
			Console.
</p>
		<p>
			Then traverse through the Registry and select the Dynamic Sequence
			Registry Resource you want to refer in your mediation login as shown
			below.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence8.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Once you click on Ok button on the Registry Browser dialog, Editor
			will update the Static Reference Key property in the Properties view
			with correct Registry Key value as shown below.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/DynamicSequence10.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
		