<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com) ~ ~ Licensed under 
	the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); ~ you may not use this file 
	except in compliance with the License. ~ You may obtain a copy of the License 
	at ~ ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 ~ ~ Unless required by 
	applicable law or agreed to in writing, software ~ distributed under the 
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS 
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. ~ See the License for the specific 
	language governing permissions and ~ limitations under the License. -->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<body>

		<h1>How To Refer a Named Sequence in ESB Graphical Editor</h1>
		<p>
			As you may already aware, Sequence in WSO2 ESB language is a
			collection
			of mediators and Named Sequence in WSO2 ESB language means
			a
			predefined Sequence element in WSO2 ESB configuration with a name so
			that other configuration elements can refer to this predefined
			Sequence and reuse the existing Sequences.
		</p>
		<p>
			WSO2 Developer Studio ESB Graphical Editor also supports referring
			Named Sequences.
		</p>
		<p>
			There are 3 methods you can refer to a Named Sequence in ESB
			Graphical
			Editor and those methods are explained in the next couple of
			sections.
		</p>
		<div class="toc">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="#method1">Drag and Drop from the Defined Sequences list in Tool Palette</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#method2">Using Sequence mediator to Refer to a Named Sequence</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					<a href="#method3">Implementing and Referring Named Sequence using Sequence Mediator</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</div>


		<h2 id="method1">Drag and Drop from the Defined Sequences list in
			Tool Palette</h2>
		<p>
			If you pay a closer attention at the ESB Graphical Editors Tool
			Palette, you will notice there is a category called “Defined
			Sequences”. And if you expand this section in the Tool Palette you
			will notice that all the Pre-Defined Sequences in your ESB
			Configuration Project are listed there in this section.
	</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence0.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			When you want to refer to a Named Sequence in your ESB configuration
			project, you can simply click on the Predefined named sequence in the
			Tool Palette and then click on the Canvas area guided by mouse
			pointer.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence2.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Then the Editor will automatically draw the Sequence in your
			mediation flow and indicate endpoints you have used in your Named
			Sequence as a part of the current mediation flow.
		</p>
		<h2 id="method2">Using Sequence mediator to Refer to a Named
			Sequence
		</h2>
		<p>When you have multiple ESB Configuration Projects in your Developer
			Studio workspace, you may want to refer a Sequence you have defined
			elsewhere than the current project. In that case, you will not be
			able to use the mechanism we explained above since we list Sequence
			only in the current ESB Configuration Project.
</p>
		<p>
			In that case you need to use some mechanism which allows you to crawl
			through your Developer Studio workspace and allow you to refer
			Sequences in another project.
</p>
		<p>
			Using Sequence Mediator allow you to fulfil your requirement as shown
			below.
</p>
		<p>
			You can click on Sequence mediator in the Tool Palette and and then
			click on the Editor Canvas ares.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence3.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>It will add the Sequence mediator to the mediation flow as shown
			below.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence4.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>When you select this Sequence mediator, you will see the Reference
			Key location setter in the Eclipse Properties view as indicated
			above. When you click on the Button at the end of this property, it
			will populate the Reference Property Key Dialog as shown below.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence5.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>

		<p>From this Dialog, you need to select “Workspace” option in order to
			select a Sequence in workspace. When you click on it, it will
			populate the Workspace Element Provider window as shown below.
</p>
		<p>
			This Workspace Element Provider Dialog will list out all the available
			Sequences in workspace categorized by Respective Project.
</p>
		<p>
			In this example project called “CardService”, there are 2 Sequences
			available as shown in the Image below.
		</p>

		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence6.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Once you select a Sequence from the list, its Name is set as the
			Reference Key.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence8.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<h2 id="method3">Implementing and Referring Named Sequence using Sequence Mediator
		</h2>

		<p>
			In the previous section you identified how you can refer to an existing
			Sequence in Developer Studio workspace using Sequence mediator.
</p>
		<p>
			In this section we are explaining you how to use Sequence mediator to
			create a new Sequence in your ESB Configuration Project and set the
			Name of the newly create Sequence as the Reference Key.
</p>
		<p>
			First again click on the Sequence Mediator in your Tool Palette and click
			on the Canvas area of the editor.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence3.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Then it will add the Sequence mediator to your mediation flow as shown
			below.
</p>
		<p>
			There you will see that you can edit the Label of the newly dragged and
			dropped Sequence Mediator. Change the name of the Label of this
			Sequence mediator and press enter.
</p>
		<p>
			It will change the Name property in the properties view as well.
</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence9.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Then Double click on the Sequence Mediator icon on the Editor and
			it will open up a new Sequence Editor with the same name you provided
			as the Label name.
		</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence10.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
		<p>Once you save the newly developed Sequence, you will see the the
			endpoints you defined in the new Sequence is shown in the mediation
			flow as shown below.</p>
		<p>
			<br></br>
			<img alt="New Server Runtime" src="images/NamedSequence11.PNG"></img>
			<br></br>
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
	
